Finding Aid for Dept. of Human Genetics (University of Michigan) records, 1937-1977
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dept. of Human Genetics (University of Michigan) records 1937-1977
University of Michigan. Dept. of Human Genetics.
0184 Bimu 2
Established in 1956, the Department of Human Genetics traces its origins to the Laboratory of the Vertebrate Biology, created in 1941, and reorganized in 1950 as the Institute of Human Biology. Following the retirement of Lee Raymond Dice, the Institute was reconfigured as a department under the direction of James V. Neel. Records consist of the correspondence and administrative files of Lee Raymond Dice and James V. Neel relating to the development of genetic research and study at Michigan. Also included are articles and reprints by Dice, Neel, and other faculty associated with genetic and heredity research at Michigan. Three photographs are also included.
4.75 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were received from the department in July 2000 (Donor # 8991 ).
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The records are open to research.
[From The University of Michigan: An Encyclopedic Survey, Volume V, The University of Michigan 1940-1975, 1977, 194-195: }
"The Department of Human Genetics had its origin in 1941, when a Heredity Clinic was established under the aegis of the Laboratory of Vertebrate Biology and the University Hospital. The clinic owed its inception to the interest of Professor Lee Dice, Director of the Laboratory, in the field of human genetics, and his conviction that the time was right to initiate a clinic which could serve both to counsel persons with inherited disorders and as a basis for research into this subject. In 1950, the Laboratory of Vertebrate Biology was reorganized as an Institute of Human Biology, and in 1956, with Dr. Dice's retirement, those parts of Institute activity concerned with human genetics became the nucleus for the present Department of Human Genetics. Originally the department was housed in some of the older hospital buildings, but in 1961, in consequence of a gift from the Buhl Foundation of Detroit, matched in magnitude by the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, the means were at hand for the construction of a building designed specifically for the needs of modern human genetics. This building, the Lawrence D. Buhl Research Center for Human Genetics, was completed in 1964. When Medical Science II was built, the Department of Human Genetics was allocated additional space immediately adjacent to the Buhl Building. The departmental facilities are among the most extensive in the United States today. Because of this early start in the field, the University has played a very significant role in the explosive development of the field of human genetics in recent years."
For additional information about the history of the department within these records, see "Heredity Clinic Annual Reports" and "History" folders in Box 1, the "Department Formation" correspondence folder in Box 4, and the "Laboratory of Vertebrate Biology/ Institute of Human Biology Annual Reports" in Box 5.
The records of the Department of Human Genetics consist of 4.75 linear feet spanning the period from 1937 to 1977 and include material from the predecessor unit, Institute of Human Biology (1941-1956). The records have been arranged in three series: Institute of Human Biology, 1941-1956; Department of Human Genetics, 1956-1977; and Reprints and Publications, 1937-1966.
The records arrived as largely unarranged departmental correspondence files of professors Lee R. Dice and James V. Neel. To make these records more accessible, they have been divided chronologically into two series at the date at which the Department of Human Genetics was officially formed, with a third series consisting of reprints and publications from all stages of the department's evolution.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Dept. of Human Genetics.; Human biology--Research--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Human genetics--Study and teaching.; Medical genetics--Study and teaching.; University of Michigan. Laboratory of Vertebrate Biology.; University of Michigan. Institute of Human Biology.
Contributors:
Neel, James V. (James Van Gundia), 1915-2000; Dice, Lee Raymond, 1887-1977.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Institute of Human Biology 1941-1956
  The series Institute of Human Biology, 1941-1956 (1.0 linear feet) includes records regarding phases prior to the formation of an official Department of Human Genetics, from the point at which all work was carried out under the auspices of the Institute of Human Biology. The largest subseries within this series is that of Correspondence and Administrative Material, arranged chronologically by year. These include departmental correspondence of Lee R. Dice (primarily up to and including 1955) and James V. Neel (primarily 1956 forward), but also includes materials regarding courses, research, committee assignments, personnel listings, accounts, proposals, department events, departmental reports, and budget. The files therefore provide a good window on the activities and developments occurring within each given year or range of years. Also of note are a procedures and forms manual from 1946, and one folder of Neel's lecture outlines from the 1940s.
  - Correspondence and Administrative Material
    - 1941-1942 (Box 1)
    - 1943-1944 (Box 1)
    - 1945 (Box 1)
    - 1946 (Box 1)
    - 1947-1948 (Box 1)
    - 1949-1950 (Box 1)
    - 1951 (Box 1)
    - 1952 (Box 1)
    - 1953 (Box 1)
    - 1954 (Box 1)
    - 1955 (Box 1)
    - 1956, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Heredity Clinic
    - Annual Reports 1945-1949 (Box 1)
    - History (timeline and correspondence) (Box 1)
  - Laboratory of Vertebrate Biology
    - Correspondence and Administrative Material
      - 1944-1947 (Box 1)
      - 1948 (Box 1)
      - 1949-1952 (Box 1)
  - Lecture Outlines, Human Heredity (Dr. Neel) 1940s (Box 1)
  - Photograph (Heredity Clinic) 1940s (Box 1)
  - Procedures Manual 1946 (Box 1)
  - Space Committee 1954 (Box 1)
- Department of Human Genetics 1956-1977
  The series Department of Human Genetics, 1956-1977 (2.75 linear feet) includes records created after the Department of Human Genetics was officially created. Again, the largest subseries is that of Correspondence and Administrative Material, arranged chronologically by year. These records are most numerous for the years 1960 to 1970, and include much the same type of materials as within the Correspondence and Administrative Material of the previous series. Also of note is one folder of materials relating to the formation of the graduate curriculum, and four folders of announcements and materials relating to seminars and colloquia from 1957 to 1977.
  - Academic Personnel Activity Reports 1974-1976 (Box 2)
  - Accreditation Review 1974-1976 (Box 2)
  - Affirmative Action 1970-1977 (Box 2)
  - Buhl Building (articles and floor plans) 1962-1963, undated (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and Administrative Material
    - 1956 (Box 2)
    - 1957 (Box 2)
    - 1958 (Box 2)
    - 1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1961, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1962, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1963, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1964, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1965, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1966, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1967, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1968, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1969, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - 1970, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - 1971 (Box 3)
    - 1972 (Box 4)
    - 1973 (Box 4)
    - 1974 (Box 4)
    - 1975 (Box 4)
    - 1976 (Box 4)
    - 1977 (Box 4)
  - Department Formation, correspondence 1956 (Box 4)
  - Department Review 1973-1974 (Box 4)
  - Graduate School Curriculum Formation 1956-1957 (Box 4)
  - Medical Center Planning, correspondence and reports 1972-1974 (Box 4)
  - Medical School Faculty Attitude Study 1971 (Box 4)
  - Office of the Vice President for Research, correspondence 1972-1977 (Box 4)
  - Photograph (Dr. Neel and students, Veteran Twin Study) 1960 (Box 4)
  - Planning Project Objectives Report 1976 (Box 4)
  - Seminars/ Colloquia
    - 1957-1959 (Box 4)
    - 1960-1965 (Box 4)
    - 1970-1977, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Visiting Scholars, correspondence and itinerary 1972-1976 (Box 4)
- Reprints and Publications 1937-1966
  The series Reprints and Publications, 1937-1966 (1.0 linear feet) consists of journal articles and reports in published form. Articles are arranged chronologically by year, with the exception of one folder of printed annual reports of the Laboratory of Vertebrate Biology/ then Institute of Human Biology, and one undated brochure of the Institute of Human Biology.
  - General
    - 1937-1948 (Box 4)
    - 1948-1949 (Box 4)
    - 1950-1952 (Box 4)
    - 1953-1954 (Box 4)
    - 1955-1956 (Box 5)
    - 1956-1957 (Box 5)
    - 1959 (Box 5)
    - 1960 (Box 5)
    - 1961 (Box 5)
    - 1962 (Box 5)
    - 1963 (Box 5)
    - 1964 (Box 5)
    - 1965 (Box 5)
    - 1966 (Box 5)
  - Institute of Human Biology Brochure undated (Box 5)
  - Laboratory of Vertebrate Biology/ Institute of Human Biology Annual Reports 1945-1956 (Box 5)
Related Materials
Also housed at the Bentley Historical Library is a collection of 5 linear feet of the personal papers of Lee R. Dice.
Personal papers of James V. Neel are housed at the American Philosophical Society in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. For information on the Neel papers at the American Philosophical Society researchers should consult the following URL:
http://www.amphilsoc.org/library/mole/n.htm